Guide to the Michael Fesco Papers MSS.602
Fales Library and Special Collections
Michael Fesco Papers
1958-2007
1974-1982
Fales Library and Special Collections
Fesco, Michael
Meyer, Dougie
MSS.602
2.25 Linear Feet In 3 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, 1 oversize flat box, 1 flat file folder, and five folders in shared boxes.
5 Quarter_Inch_Audio_Reel
Michael Fesco (1934-2019) was a Broadway dancer and major figure in New York City's gay nightlife scene. From 1974 to 1981, he owned and managed The Flamingo, New York City's first exclusively gay disco. The club was located at the corner of Houston and Broadway and was only open to club members. In addition to regular dance nights, The Flamingo hosted themed parties with elaborate set pieces and themed decor. After closing The Flamingo in 1981, Fesco remained active in the gay nightlife scene and hosted events at other venues, including Studio 54. The Michael Fesco Papers (dated 1958-2007, bulk dates 1974-1982) document Fesco's career in theater and nightlife. The bulk of the materials are related to The Flamingo and document the club's origins, annual theme parties, and eventual closure in 1981. These materials include photographs, posters, correspondence, invitations, member newsletters, audio recordings, and a small selection of artifacts, including buttons, matches, and a lighter. Fesco's Broadway career is documented with correspondence, a handbill, and one scrapbook, and his post-Flamingo work in nightlife is documented by posters, invitations, and a second scrapbook.
Scope and Contents
The Michael Fesco Papers (dated 1958-2007, bulk dates 1975-1982) contain materials documenting Michael Fesco's career as a Broadway dancer, nightclub owner, and party producer. The collection documents gay nightlife in New York City in the 1970s and early 1980s, and the emergence of exclusive gay membership clubs during that period.
This collection is primarily focused on The Flamingo, the gay, members-only nightclub that Fesco owned and operated from 1974 to 1981. Fesco's time operating The Flamingo is documented through the Flamingo Flash newsletter, press clippings, party invitations, posters, correspondence, a list of members, and ephemera, including napkins, buttons, matches, and a lighter. There are also photographs and slides that depict performances, party sets, and renovations at The Flamingo, and show prominent party guests, including Andy Warhol, Divine, fashion model Norma Jean, and artist Victor Hugo. The collection also contains slides showing an early Calvin Klein fashion show which was held at the Flamingo in 1975. Fesco regularly employed DJs, and this collection includes audio recordings of sets by Howard Merrit and Armando Galvez on magnetic sound tape. He also hosted exhibitions at The Flamingo for artists including Richard Karowski, Joe Minimitello, and Michel Lablais.
Some photographs taken at Flamingo parties and events contain nudity. Photographic slides in box 5, folder 24 include images of sex acts.
Michael Fesco's career in theater is documented with correspondence, a hand bill, photographs of him performing in a 1966 production of Oklahoma!, and a scrapbook that contains news clipping and copies of Actor's Equity contracts. The collection also includes a flyer for a party planned by Fesco at the Ice Palace on Fire Island. Fesco's freelance party planning, including his work with Labelle and Lynne Carter, are documented in photographs, party invitations, event tickets, promotional materials, and press clippings, many of which he placed in a second scrapbook.
The Michael Fesco Papers also include slides showing aspects of Fesco's personal life, such as the renovation of his Brooklyn house and vacations with friends.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection have been grouped by topic and arranged in chronological order.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Dougie Meyer in August 2019; the accession number associated with this gift is 2020.034.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Fales Library and Special Collections, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Biographical Note
Michael Fesco (1934-2019) was a Broadway dancer and major figure in New York City's gay nightlife scene. He moved to New York City in 1958 to study ballet and worked as a dancer in Broadway productions. In 1969, he took a summer job working at a nightclub in Cherry Grove on Fire Island, where he later designed and opened the Ice Palace. At the Ice Palace, Fesco focused on dance music and regularly employed DJs, something that was unusual at the time. He also created the "tea dance" to attract customers to the club on typically slow Sunday afternoons. In 1973, he decided to focus on gay nightlife in Manhattan, and he opened The Flamingo in 1974, where he continued to employ DJs, host regular dance nights, and produce themed parties until 1981. The Flamingo was a members-only club located on the corner of Houston and Broadway and was one of the first discos explicitly created for gay men. Fesco did freelance event planning and promotion both before and after operating The Flamingo, using the company name "Michael Fesco Presents" in the 1970s and "Michael Fesco Productions" beginning in the 1980s. He had long-term relationships with the singing group Labelle and drag performer Lynne Carter, both of whom he worked with throughout the 1970s and 1980s under both company names. In the early 1980s, many Michael Fesco Presents parties were at Studio 54, and Fesco later planned parties at other clubs, including Club West End and The Roxy. He also created "Sea Tea" parties in the late 1990s, which were tea dances held on boats sailing around Manhattan. In addition to tea dances, Fesco planned annual Halloween, Christmas, New Year's Eve, and season opening and closing parties, as well as parties with themes including "Tropicana," "Tattooed Cowboy," "Black Party," "White Party," "Follies," and "Carnival."
Appraisal
In 2024, pornographic slides were removed from the collection. Unlike The Flamingo party slides depicting sex acts, these pictures were not taken in public and the subjects' faces were showing. They were removed protect the privacy of the subjects.
Posters.; Photographs.; Gay discotheques -- New York (State) -- New York.; Gay business enterprises -- New York (State) -- New York; Gay men -- United States -- Social life and customs.; Nightclubs -- New York (State) -- New York.; The Flamingo (New York, N.Y.); Meyer, Dougie; Studio 54 (Nightclub)
- Theater and Dance, 1958-1966 (Box 5, Folder 1, Box Shared Fales 110, Folder 5)
- Theater Scrapbook, 1963-1964 (Box Shared Fales 110, Folder 6)
- Michael Fesco Portraits, 1972-1974 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Ice Palace, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Labelle, 1973, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 13, Box Shared Fales 110, Folder 5)
- Lynne Carter Performance, circa early 1970s (Box 2, Quarter inch audio reel 602.004)
- Michael Fesco Presents, 1974 (Box Shared Fales 110, Folder 5, Box 4, Folder 1-2, Box Shared Fales 097, Folder 12)
- Flamingo Renovations, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Flamingo Membership, 1974-1981 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Flamingo Flash, 1974-1981 (Box 5, Folder 6-12)
- Theme Parties at The Flamingo, 1974-1981 (Box 5, Folder 14-24, Box 4, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Some of the slides in box 5, folder 24 contain nudity and depict sex acts.
- Flamingo Party Photographs, undated, circa 1974-1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Famous Flamingo Patrons, undated, circa 1974-1981 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
- The Flamingo Interior Photographs, undated, circa 1974-1981 (Box 1, Folder 4, Box Shared Fales 109, Folder 16, Folder 8)
- Art Exhibitions at The Flamingo, undated, circa 1974-1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Flamingo Ephemera, 1974-1981 (Box 3)
- Calvin Klein Show at The Flamingo, May 1975 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Untitled Audio Recording, November 1977 (Box 2, Quarter inch audio reel 602.002)
- Howard Merrit at The Flamingo, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Quarter inch audio reel 602.001, 602.005)
- Armando at The Flamingo, 1978 (Box 2, Quarter inch audio reel 602.003)
- The Flamingo Press Clippings, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- The Flamingo Correspondence, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- The Flamingo Closing, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Michael Fesco Productions Scrapbook, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 9-10, Box Shared Fales 109, Folder 13-14)
- Michael Fesco Productions Parties, 1981-2000 (Box 1, Folder 11, Box Shared Fales 109, Folder 15, Box Shared Fales 097, Folder 8)
- Personal Photographs, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Brooklyn House Photographs, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Press Clippings, 1991-2007 (Box Shared Fales 110, Folder 5)